Finding Aid for Robert M. Warner Papers, 1945-2007
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Robert M. Warner papers 1945-2007 1980-1992
Warner, Robert Mark, 1927-
89405 Aa 2
Historian and archivist at the University of Michigan, archivist of the United States, dean of the University of Michigan School of Information and Library Studies. Records, 1980-1985, detailing his activities as Archivist of the United States; documentation prepared by Warner in 1972 and submitted to the Indian Claims Commission relating primarily to Indian land claims in Michigan and Ohio; files detailing archival career interests, as director of the Michigan Historical Collections (now Bentley Historical Library) and as a member of the Society of American Archivists.
37.5 linear feet
8 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Robert M. Warner in multiple donations between 1990 and 2005. His children made a final donation in July 2007. (Donor No. 3808 ).
No further additions to the records are expected.
The papers are open with the exception of some student records in box 38 subject to FIRPA restrictions and Warner's diaries from his time at NARA, boxes 1, 2 and 37, which are closed until 2017.
Archivist, historian and professor, Robert Mark Warner was born on June 28, 1927, in Montrose, Colorado, son of Mark Thomas and Bertha Margaret (Rich) Warner. Warner completed his undergraduate work in history at Muskingum College in New Concord, Ohio in 1949. It was here he met Eleanor Jane Bullock, whom he married in 1954. After a year as a high school teacher of history and speech in Montrose, he was drafted into the U.S. Army where he served in Germany, from 1950 to 1952, during the Korean War. Upon his return, Warner continued his education at the University of Michigan where he earned an M.A. (1953) and a Ph.D. (1958) in history. Warner's studies concentrated on "recent" history (then defined as 1876 to the 1950s). After completing his doctoral degree, Warner joined the faculty of the history department of the University of Michigan where he taught Michigan history. In 1974, he was invited by Dean Russell Bidlack to join the faculty of the University of Michigan School of Library Science and inaugurate the archival studies program.
Warner's association with archives began during his early years as a graduate student, when he used the University of Michigan's Michigan Historical Collections (MHC) to do research. When a position as a research assistant in the Collections became available, Warner took his first step down a completely different road than he had imagined his career would take. During his years at the MHC, he was active in several professional archival organizations, including the International Council on Archives (ICA) and the Society of American Archivists (SAA). Warner was particularly active in SAA, where he served on the Council, as secretary, director, vice president and president, as well as many committees. By 1966, Warner had become director of the MHC (now known as the Bentley Historical Library), a position that he held until his appointment as Archivist of the United States in 1980.
When Warner arrived at the National Archives and Records Services (NARS) in July of 1980, the organization had been without leadership for nearly a year, since the resignation of his predecessor James B. (Bert) Rhoads in 1979. Warner described the atmosphere that greeted him as one of demoralization and high tension. Friction had developed between NARS and its parent organization, the General Services Administration (GSA), over perceived interference and inappropriate intervention of GSA in archival matters. GSA Administrator Admiral Roland G. Freeman's plan to relocate federal records to regional Federal Records Centers around the country caused uproar in NARS and among scholars and archival and historical organizations around the country. NARS also faced an investigation by Congress and the Executive Branch over preservation activities and suffered from management problems.
Warner's major accomplishment as Archivist of the U.S. was to secure the independence of the National Archives from GSA. While President Franklin D. Roosevelt had originally created the National Archives as an independent agency in 1934, by the 1950s it had become a subdivision of the GSA. As early as 1968, a movement to free NARS from the GSA had been launched, but quickly foundered. Bills were introduced in the Senate in 1980 and 1981, but failed to come to a vote. In 1982, the Smithsonian Study came out, recommending autonomy, but was rejected by GSA Administrator Gerald Carmen. By 1983 it had become clear to Warner that NARS could no longer remain a captive of GSA if it was to be an effective organization. With the support of Senator Mark Hatfield of Oregon and several other key figures in Washington, the National Archives and Administration Act of 1983 was introduced in the Senate on March 23, 1983 (S. 905). In September, the bill was introduced in the House as H.R. 3987. As the bill made its way through congress, Warner worked behind the scenes, generating support and attention from such organizations as SAA, the American Historical Association and such figures as Barbara Tuchman, Alex Haley and Ed Meese. In June of 1984, the Senate passed the bill, followed by the House in August. After going to conference, the Senate and the House passed the revised bill on October 3 and 4, 1984, respectively. President Ronald Reagan signed the Act on October 19, 1984, creating the independent National Archives and Records Administration (NARA), effective April 1, 1985.
Other highlights of Warner's years at NARS included the completion of a twenty-year preservation plan in 1984, the creation of a technology assessment division, the completion of the appraisal and retention plan for FBI records in 1981, controversy over the Richard Nixon Presidential papers, as well as the founding of the Carter Library and planning of the Ronald Reagan Library.
By the end of 1984, Warner had decided to resign his position as Archivist of the U.S. in order to return to the University of Michigan, where he would become Dean of the School of Information and Library Studies (SILS). Warner stayed on at NARS until April 1985, after which he took up his new position at the University of Michigan. Under Warner's leadership, SILS revised its master and PhD programs and emphasized faculty research and minority hiring, moved to a new location at West Hall, fully re-organized its staff structure. From 1988 to 1991, Warner also served as acting director of the University of Michigan Library and was given the lifetime title of University Historian. He retired from the deanship in 1992, and was succeeded by Daniel Atkins.
Warner spent one year teaching at the School of Library and Information Science at UCLA. He was also involved with the National Library of Education Task Force and actively served on the University of Michigan History and Traditions Committee. Warner also served on two General Accounting Office (GAO) committees, the Research and Education Panel (REAP) and the History Advisory Program, as well as the Foundation of the National Archives. From 1986 to 2007 Warner served on various boards and committees including the Executive Committee of the University of Michigan Library, Clarke Historical Library, Presbyterian Historical Society and others. He was also secretary for the Gerald R. Ford Foundation
In 1995, Warner published a memoir on his experience at the National Archives called "Diary of a Dream." In 2005, Dr. Warner was honored for his lasting contribution to the National Archives with the naming of the Robert M. Warner Research Center at the newly renovated downtown building, in Washington, D.C.
Warner died at age 79, on April 24, 2007 in Ann Arbor, Michigan.
The Robert M. Warner Papers date from 1945 to 2007. These materials primarily highlight Warner's lengthy professional career, documenting his various teaching and administrative positions at the University of Michigan, his appointment as Archivist of the United States and the subsequent administration at the National Archives. Also documented is the appointment of his successor at the National Archives, his return to the University of Michigan as Dean of the School of Information and Library Science, and his activities on various boards and foundations after his retirement. Much of the records documenting his tenure as the director of the Michigan Historical Collections (now the Bentley Historical Library) can be found under the official Bentley Historical Library record group.
The Robert M. Warner collection has been divided into ten series: Biography; Correspondence; Indian Court Claims; National Archives; School of Information and Library Science and Dean of the Michigan Library Systems; Teaching Materials and Scholarly Research; Professional Activities, Speeches; Scrapbooks and Scrapbook Materials, and Audio-Visual Material.
Subjects:
Bentley Historical Library.; Indians of North America--Michigan.; Land use--Michigan.; Michigan Historical Collections.; Society of American Archivists.; United States. Indian Claims Commission.; United States. National Archives and Records Service.; University of Michigan. School of Information and Library Studies.; Warner, Robert M. (Robert Mark), 1927-2007.; Land use--Ohio.
- Biographical
  The Biography series consists of two subseries: Biographical Material, and Diaries. The Biographical Material subseries (.25 feet) includes copies of academic curricula vitae and biographical sketches that span his entire career.
  - Biography and CVs
    - Biographical sketches and CV (Box 1)
    - Clippings (Box 1)
    - NARA Biographical Material (Box 1)
    - University of Michigan Faculty Biographical Data (Box 1)
    - Vita (Box 1)
  - Diaries
    The Diaries subseries (1.75 linear feet) consists primarily of transcriptions of dictations Warner made during his time at the National Archives (see the Audio Visual series for some of the actual cassette tapes). Warner reviewed and corrected many of the transcriptions and relied heavily on the diaries when writing his book Diary of a Dream. The early parts of this series are donor notes from traveling to visit donors for the Michigan Historical Collections in the 1960s and 1970s. Warner continued keeping a personal and professional diary though 2000. The Diaries are restricted until 2017.
    [RESTRICTED until 2017 ]
    - 1951-1952 (Box 1)
    - 1956-1959 (Box 1)
    - 1960-1972 (Box 1)
    - 1974-1975 (Box 1)
    - 1976 January-April (Box 1)
    - 1976 May-December (Box 1)
    - 1977 (Box 1)
    - 1978 January-May (Box 1)
    - 1978 June-September (Box 1)
    - 1978 October-December (Box 1)
    - 1979 January-March (Box 1)
    - 1979 April-November (Box 1)
    - 1980 January-May (Box 1)
    - 1980 June-December (Box 1)
    - 1981 January-May (Box 1)
    - 1981 June-December (Box 1)
    - 1982 January-July (Box 1)
    - 1982 August-December (Box 1)
    - 1983 January-May (Box 1)
    - 1983 June-December (Box 1)
    - 1984 January-May (Box 2)
    - 1984 June-December (Box 2)
    - 1985 (Box 2)
    - 1986 January-May (Box 2)
    - 1986 May-December (Box 2)
    - 1987 (Box 2)
    - 1988 (Box 2)
    - 1989-1990 (Box 2)
    - 1991-1994 (Box 2)
    - 1995-1996 (Box 2)
    - 1997-2000 (Box 2)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series (5 linear feet) consists of both professional and personal correspondence. The first box consists of miscellaneous correspondence organized by date 1945-1993. The next two boxes consist of Warner's correspondence in the 1990s and maintains Warner's alphabetical arrangement. Included here is a folder dedicated solely to correspondence regarding Don Wilson, former Archivist of the United States whose career was tinged with controversy due to the Bush administration's threatened destruction of e-mail records in 1993. The fourth box holds letters from Jane to her Aunt between 1983-1985 and letters from Jane to her some Mark, known as "Bunkie" throughout the 1980s. These letters are frequent, from a few per month to a few per week, and describe Jane's personal activities, the whereabouts of the Warner family, as well as many aspects of Robert's professional life. The fourth box also holds a shoebox labeled "Daddy's Love Letters" (1949-1954 bulk 1952-1954), which mostly are from Robert to Jane and cover the period when he was in the Army stationed in Europe and his early time in Ann Arbor. There are also some letters from Jane to her parents in Ohio from the same vintage. The fifth box contains Personal Correspondence from Jane Warner to her mother and Aunt Eleanor Bullock ("Auntie") from 1962 to 1982. Researches can find official correspondence from Warner's time at the National Archives in the National Archives series.
  - By Date:
    - 1945-1949 (Box 3)
    - 1950 (Army) (Box 3)
    - 1951 (Army) (Box 3)
    - 1952 (Army) (Box 3)
    - 1953-1956 (Box 3)
    - 1955-1957 (Box 3)
    - 1958 (Box 3)
    - 1959 (Box 3)
    - 1960-1961 (Box 3)
    - 1962-1964 (Box 3)
    - 1965-1969 (Box 3)
    - 1970-1973 (Box 3)
    - 1974-1976 (Box 3)
    - 1977-1979 (Box 3)
    - 1980 (Box 3)
    - 1981 (Box 3)
    - 1982 (Box 3)
    - 1983 (Box 3)
    - 1984 (Box 3)
    - 1985 (Box 3)
    - 1986 (Box 3)
    - 1987 (Box 3)
    - 1988 (Box 3)
    - 1989 (Box 3)
    - 1990-1991 (Box 3)
    - 1992 (Box 3)
    - 1993 (Box 3)
  - Program Files of the Archivist's Office: Letters of Congratulations on appointment s Archives of the US
    - A-B (Box 4)
    - C-E (Box 4)
    - F-J (Box 4)
    - K-M (Box 4)
    - Mc-R (Box 4)
    - S-Z (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
  - Correspondence By last name or subject first initial 1988-1999
    - A-B (Box 4)
    - Archives Amendment (Box 4)
    - Azazels (Box 4)
    - Black Canyon (Box 4)
    - Bentley Library (Box 4)
    - C (Box 4)
    - Carlin, John W (Box 4)
    - Clements Library (Box 4)
    - Coleman, Mary Sue (Box 4)
    - D (Box 4)
    - Department of History, Arts, and Libraries (HAL, Michigan) (Box 4)
    - E (Box 4)
    - Engler, John (Box 4)
    - F (Box 5)
    - Ford (Box 5)
    - Ford Library (Box 5)
    - Frost (Box 5)
    - G (Box 5)
    - H-I (Box 5)
    - History & Traditions -- Galler (Box 5)
    - J (Box 5)
    - K (Box 5)
    - King, John L (Box 5)
    - L (Box 5)
    - M-N (Box 5)
    - Middleton, H (Box 5)
    - NARA (Box 5)
    - NARA 20th Anniversary (Box 5)
    - NEH (Box 5)
    - O (Box 5)
    - P-Q (Box 5)
    - R (Box 5)
    - Retirement (Box 5)
    - S-T (Box 5)
    - SI (Box 5)
    - U-V-W (Box 5)
    - Weinstein, Allen (Box 5)
    - Wilson, Don (Box 5)
    - X-Y-Z (Box 5)
  - Personal Letters
    - Letters from Jane to Eleanor Bullock ("Auntie") 1983-1985 (Box 6)
    - Letters from Jane to Eleanor Bullock ("Auntie") 1986 (Box 6)
    - Letters from Robert to Jane 1949-1954 with some letters from Jane to her Parents, 1952, 1 shoe box (Box 6)
    - Letters from Jane Warner to Mark "Bunkie" Warner (Box 6)
    - Personal Letters from Jane Warner to her Mother, and Eleanor Bullock ("Auntie") 1962-1983 (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Warner Cottage at Surfwood in Harbor Springs (Box 7)
    - Contracts (Box 7)
    - Dissertation Committees (Box 7)
- Indian Court Claims Research
  The Indian Court Claims Research series (2 linear feet) contains of two linear feet of various court docket information and research materials compiled by Warner for various Indian claims court cases while he was the head of the Michigan Historical Collections.
  - Documentation prepared by Warner and submitted to the Indian Claims Commission relating to claims in Michigan and Ohio 1972
    - Docket 146, 15-M and 40-K: Ottawa-Potawatomi Indians (Box 8)
    - Docket 57: Saginaw Chippewa Indians (Box 8)
    - Dockets 18-R and 18-F: Bay Mills Indian Community (Box 8)
    - Docket 18-E and 58: Ottawa-Chippewa Indians (Box 8)
    - Docket 212 and 213: Wyandot Indians (Box 8)
    - Docket 212 and 213: Wyandot Indians (Box 9)
      (continued)
    - Notes and research documents for Wyandot Indian Cases (Box 9)
    - Indian Projects (Box 9)
- National Archives
  The series, National Archives materials (5 linear feet; 1976-1985) are divided into twelve subseries: Correspondence, Briefing/Orientation Materials, Personal Files on Current Issues, Long Range Planning Goals, Statements/Hearings, NARS Independence, Preservation, Presidential Libraries, FBI Records, Task Forces, Topical Files, and Miscellaneous files.
  - Pre-Appointment Correspondence
    The first subseries is correspondence concerning Warner's appointment as Archivist of the United States, covering from July 1979 to July 1980. The National Archives (Pre-Warner Administration) records include letters exchanged during the late 1970s between Warner and Virginia Purdy of the National Archives Assembly. Included are correspondence and newspaper clippings documenting the resignation of Warner's predecessor as Archivist of the United States, James B. (Bert) Rhoads.
    - Correspondence re: appointment at NARS July 1979-July 1980, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Emergency Committee to Preserve the National Archives January 1979-February 1980 (Box 10)
  - National Archives (Pre-Warner administration) (Box 10)
  - Federal Records Work
    The Federal Records Work series contains materials that document Warner's work on the appraisal and preservation of federal records including materials pertaining to a 1976 Congressional panel discussion, a Senatorial papers conference in 1978, a subsequent proposal regarding the accessioning of these papers, and correspondence relating to the Emergency Committee to Preserve the National Archives (1979 to February 1980).
    - Congressional Panel Discussion 1976, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Senatorial Papers Conference September 1978 (Box 10)
    - Senatorial Papers Proposal 1979-1980 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence
    The Correspondence subseries includes letters exchanged between Warner and University of Michigan faculty members during most of his administration, 1980 to 1984. Also significant is a folder of correspondence with Keijo Virtanen, historian at the University of Turku's (Finland) Institute of History of Civilization, which spans from 1980 to 1985. Eleven folders contain correspondence relating to NARS and cover the majority of the period from January 1980 to April 1985. Of special note are materials pertaining to the replacement of Warner as Archivist during the independence struggle. More correspondence items are located in the general Correspondence series.
    - University of Michigan 1980-1984 (Box 10)
    - Keijo Virtanen August 1980-March 1985 (Box 10)
    - NARS (personal) January 1980-April 1985, 11 folders (Box 10)
    - Correspondence re: Replacement of Archivist of U.S. February 1983-July 1983 (Box 11)
  - Briefing/Orientation Materials
    Briefing and orientation materials, prepared especially for Warner as a means of introduction to the National Archives, are divided topically. These materials include a summary of NARS, as well as briefings on the presidential libraries, the National Historic Publications and Records Committee (NHPRC), and the Assistant to the Deputy Archivist, and the Office of the Executive Director.
    - Summary of NARS (Box 11)
    - Presidential Libraries, 3 folders (Box 11)
    - General Counsel (Box 11)
    - Functions of Assistant to Deputy Archivist (Box 11)
    - NHPRC (National Historic Publications and Records Commission) (Box 11)
    - Office of Educational Programs (Box 11)
    - Office of Federal Register (Box 11)
    - Office of the Executive Director (Box 11)
  - Personal Files on Current Issues
    Warner's personal files on current issues consist of three folders. The original titles of the first two folders, "Significant Documents" and "Personal Notes on Sensitive Matters," were retained. Records in the former cover July 1980 to May 1981. The latter, containing records that date from 1980 to 1983, includes materials about NARS independence, the Technology Assessment Division, the presidential libraries, personnel issues, general issues and a draft of a statement on records management. Of special note is a draft of a resignation letter written in October 1983 by Warner when he was considering giving up his post. A third folder contains plans and notes on current issues dating from July 1980 to April 1983.
    - "Significant Documents," July 1980-May 1981 (Box 11)
    - "Personal Notes on Sensitive Matters" 1980-1983 (Box 11)
    - Plans and Notes July 1982-April 1983 (Box 11)
  - Long Range Planning Goals
    Materials documenting NARS's long-range planning goals comprise two folders. The first folder, arranged chronologically, covers Warner's administration from 1980 to 1985. Records in the second folder date from 1983 and are a more detailed, section-by-section plan.
    - 1980-1985 (Box 11)
    - Section-by-section 1983 (Box 11)
  - Statements/Hearings
    The Statements/Hearings subseries contains the statements that Warner presented before a number of committees as well as documents related to those hearings. Among these topically arranged materials are statements pertaining to NARS programs made before the Subcommittee of the House Committee on Appropriations in March 1982 and the Subcommittee on Treasury, Postal Service and General Government in March 1983. Another folder contains a statement regarding NARS independence, dated October 1981, but it is not clear where the statement was presented.
    - Subpoena, Senate Foreign Relations Committee 1981 (Box 11)
    - Oversight Hearings, re: Preservation March 1982 (Box 11)
    - Senatorial Records May 1982 (Box 11)
    - Subcommittee of House committee on Appropriations, re: NARS Programs March 1982 (Box 11)
    - Subcommittee on Treasury, Postal Service and General Government, re: NARS Programs March 1983 (Box 11)
    - Government Information, Justice and Agriculture Subcommittee of Committee on Government Operations April 1983 (Box 11)
    - Statement re: NARS Independence October 1981 (Box 11)
    - Subcommittee on Treasury, Postal Service and General Government January 1982-March 1982 (Box 11)
    - Subcommittee on Civil Service, Post Office and General Services of the Senate Committee on Governmental Affairs October 1981 (Box 11)
    - Congressional Budget Hearings for 1986 (Box 11)
  - NARS Independence
    The largest section of the collection traces the development of the independence movement at NARS. The materials, arranged topically and chronologically, include articles and position statements from 1981, statements and supporting documents for Warner's testimony on S. 905 (the National Archives and Records Administration Act of 1983) and the hearings on that bill. Miscellaneous materials related to the independence movement are divided into folders and arranged chronologically. One of these folders contains a key report produced as the result of a task force investigation on the status of the Smithsonian Institution, comparing it to the National Archives.
    - Articles and Position Statements 1981 (Box 11)
    - NARS Autonomy Plan 1981 (Box 11)
    - H.R. 6894 Draft, 1982 (Box 11)
    - Statements and Supporting Documents for Testimony on S. 905 1983 (Box 11)
    - Hearings on S. 905 July 1983 (Box 11)
    - "Operation Exit" [Notes and Lobbying Efforts] 1983-1984 (Box 11)
    - NARA Act of 1984 Presentation Copy (Box 11)
    - Reference File, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Reorganizational Plans (Box 12)
    - Misc. 1981-1983 (Box 12)
    - Misc. 1983, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Misc. 1983 & 1984, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Misc. 1984, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Congressional Publications
      - S. 1421--National Archives and Records Act of 1981 (Box 12)
      - Hearings before Subcommittee of Committee on Government Operations (H.R.) March 1982 (Box 12)